White Storm (Part 2)
I'm not sure why,
（零(れい)）なぜだろう？
but it all came flooding back.
急に思い出したんだ
Souya?
（島田(しまだ)）宗谷(そうや)？
（島田）そうだな…
Let's see...
（零）子供のころ—
When I was a kid,
there was once a white bird with huge wings that had wandered
家の庭に迷い込んだ大きな翼の…
白い鳥
into our yard.
He reminds me of a bird.
（島田）鳥に似てる
Master Souya is wearing traditional Japanese garb!
（関係者Ａ）宗谷名人が和服だ！
I thought it was normal for both players
to wear suits for commemorative matches.
（関係者Ｂ）記念対局は
双方 スーツが通常だったよな
（神宮寺(じんぐうじ)）いやぁ 助かりましたよ
遠野(とおの)名誉九段
You're a lifesaver, Touno Meiyo, 9-dan!
Not at all. I'm glad the match is in my town.
（遠野）いやいや
地元開催のときで良かった
My kimono hobby was finally of use to someone.
わしの着物道楽が
やっと役に立ちましたよ
I'm honored that Master Souya is wearing one of them.
宗谷名人に着てもらえるなぞ
名誉なことです
That'll be a family heirloom now.
家宝にさせてもらいますよ
（零）不思議だ
It's strange.
He's supposed to be like a character who's always been in a book.
ずっと
物語の中にいたはずなのに—
But now, he's sitting before me.
今 目の前に座っている
He's breathing and moving.
息をして 動いている
そして 僕と 戦うという
And he's going to play against me.
しっかりしろ！
昨日 自分で言ったじゃないか
Get it together.
Didn't you say it yourself last night?
I want to concentrate as I play so the
match isn't over as soon as it's begun.
（零）あっという間に
終わってしまわないように—
集中して指したい …です
Right now,
今から僕は
この人と渡り合わねばならないのだ
I have to cross paths with this person.
力の差など分かりきっている
I'm well aware of the gap in our abilities.
But if I jump into this with anything other than the intention of winning,
だが “勝つため”以外の心で
飛び込んだら—
my head will get blown off in an instant.
一瞬で首を吹っ飛ばされる
Let's have a good match.
お願いします
Among the freshly blooming dandelions
And the droplets of water which couldn't quite become snow
I thought I could make out a face stained with tears
So I offered my umbrella without a second thought
Is going left or right correct?
The path ended before I could really decide
But surely the right call is the one which spares that special someone
From any painful experiences
So with a little courage, take that plunge forward
If everything's all crooked, take an oblique path
As long as you're moving forward, you'll find the light
Like those little birds that huddle together and cry out in unison
We'll definitely ring in the start of a new season
And so spring will embrace us once more
We'll splash paint on some new pages
We became fast friends, we enjoyed some good food
We might've even argued a little
But we carry those little moments in our hearts
As reasons which compel us toward a future that can't possibly be mistaken
No matter how many times we find ourselves lost among sunlit trees
Today has been carried here by the winds on a one-way ticket
That blooms into a perfect day
（関係者Ｄ）相矢倉(あいやぐら)か
（関係者Ｅ）初手合わせだからな
Double Fortress defense, huh?
It is their first match together.
Well, I suppose they both want to get to know each other.
（関係者Ｅ）まあ お互いを
しっかり知っておこうというとこか
Maybe it just happened naturally during the course of play.
（関係者Ｆ）自然に
指し合っているって流れですかな
（関係者Ｄ）うん？　宗谷 ２八銀
（関係者Ｅ）２八銀？
Souya moved a silver to 2h.
S-2h?
ホホッ…　質問状じゃな
It's a question.
Souya is asking, "Hello. Who is this?"
宗谷君からの
“もしもし
あなたは誰ですか”ってな
S-2h.
（零）２八銀
この手は初めてだ　研究か？
I haven't seen that move before.
Is he testing me?
…ということは ３八飛 １九銀成
How about...
R-3h.
S-1i+.
S4h-5g.
５七銀右 ８三香 …か
Then ending with L-8c?
It's certainly a threat, but it's too straightforward.
確かに脅威だけれど 直線的すぎる
直撃さえ避ければ問題ない
It's no problem as long as I avoid a direct attack.
むしろ 今行くべきは
密集している あの—
In fact, I should be moving my pieces into a close formation.
With a...
角頭(かくとう)だ
Bishop Head's Pawn push.
（関係者Ｇ）いやぁ
しかし 桐山(きりやま) よく戦ってるよ
Still, Kiriyama is putting up a good fight.
I guess it's no surprise he was the next person to turn pro in junior high after Souya.
（関係者Ｈ）さすが 宗谷に次いで
中学生プロになっただけある
（関係者Ｉ）う〜ん…
むしろ この段階じゃ—
Actually, at this stage,
it looks like Kiriyama has the upper hand.
桐山のほうが
いいくらいじゃないのか？
But if a newcomer 5-dan has the upper hand on the current Master in the midgame,
（関係者Ｊ）
いやいや　新人の五段と
現名人の対局の中盤で—
“新人のほうが
むしろ優勢か”とか来たら—
then, if this were a TV show,
that'd be a sign the newbie's going to lose.
それは もう ドラマだったら
ただの敗北フラグだろう
（遠野）ホホホッ…
議論が起きるだけ大したもんじゃ
Getting a discussion going shows how well he's doing.
（遠野）それだけのもんが—
That alone shows he has something going.
あの子の中にあるってことじゃ
That's right.
（零）
そうだ　５五歩 同銀左 ７五歩
P*5e.
S6fx5e.
Px7e.
And then I aim for the bishop...
ここで ねらいどおり 角頭を…
P*7d.
７四歩だ
Why did I feel a faint shooting pain in
my fingertips when I let go of the piece?
なぜだろう？
駒から手を離すとき
指先に かすかに痛みが走った
P*7d.
７四歩…
No.
違う
何やってんだ 俺！
What the hell am I doing?
Why didn't I realize?
なんで気づかない？
８六歩があるだろう！
There's a P-8f play!
If he hits me with P-8f,
ここで ８六歩と とがめられたら
もう あとがない！
it's all over!
P-8f.
８六歩…
ンンッ…　ハァ…
（零）同歩…
Px8f.
９五角
B-9e.
G6g-7g.
７七金寄
Souya dropped a pawn at 8e.
（関係者Ｍ）
宗谷 ８五歩　桐山 これは厳しいか
Kiriyama's in a tough spot.
What will you do?
（関係者Ｎ）どうする？
（関係者Ｏ）同歩と取るか？
Go with Px8e?
P-9f! Not Px8e!
（関係者Ａ）
９六歩！　同歩じゃない
I see!
（どよめき）
そうか ８五歩を同歩と取ると—
If he took the pawn at 8e with his pawn, it'd be answered by the knight at 9c, leaving his king wide open.
９三桂と跳ねられて
玉頭(ぎょくとう)が支えきれない
It makes sense.
（関係者Ｐ）
なるほど　だが ここまでだろう
But this might be it.
That P*7d from before hurt.
（関係者Ｐ）さっきの７四歩が痛い
Yeah, but at least he dodged Souya's P*8e.
（関係者Ａ）いや
でも 宗谷の８五歩は かわしたぞ
Well, well, +L-6h.
（遠野）おやおや　６八成香とは
Now Souya's making interesting moves.
宗谷君も
また悩ましい手を指してくる
So Kiriyama, 5-dan,
さてさて 桐山五段
would you take this promoted lance with the rook or not?
この成香を飛車で取るか取らぬか
The correct answer is...
正解は…
（遠野）おお　エサには手を出さず
じっと ７三歩成
He didn't take the bait, but instead went with P-7c+.
He's making the best moves in a matter-of-fact way.
淡々と最善手を指してくるのぅ
Sheesh.
まったく　だから こいつは面白い
That's what makes him interesting.
After that, I was absorbed in the match.
（零）それからは夢中だった
（駒を打つ音）
The sound of each piece on the board was
accompanied by a flash of light in my head.
頭の中で駒音が フラッシュを
たいたみたいに バチバチと光った
I realized that something in my head was connecting all of the moves.
頭の中で何かが どんどん
手をつなげていくのが分かった
まるで…
It was like...
silvery, dazzling water,
銀色に光る まぶしい水が—
flowing into every nook and cranny.
隅々にまで
流れ込んでいくようだった
White Storm (Part 2)
White Storm (Part 3)
（零）
指した７四歩から手を離すとき—
When I let go of my pawn at 7d,
it felt like the surface of my fingers was being ripped off.
指の表面を
引き剥がすような感覚があった
手を離した瞬間に
敗着だと気がついた
The moment I took my hand away,
I realized that move would cost me the match.
もう あとがなくなったことが
分かった
I knew it was over.
But at the same time, it crossed my mind.
…と同時に ふと思った
If I only played the best moves from this point on,
もし ここからの手を全て
最善手のみで指し通せたとしたら…
how far could I go in the match?
この将棋は
どこまで行けるのかなって
The wind is strong.
風 強いな　台風
太平洋に抜けるんじゃないのか？
I thought the typhoon was just
going to pass through the Pacific.
I hope the trains keep running.
止まったりしないといいな
I want to go to my afternoon classes so it's only counted as a half-day absence.
午後からは授業に出て
半日休み扱いにしてほしいんだけど
There's Souya.
宗谷さんだ
そっか　同じ新幹線か
I see.
We're on the same bullet train, huh?
He's going back on the early train too.
随分 早い列車で戻るんだな
I figured he was the type who didn't hang around,
but it's still surprising.
長居はしないタイプだとは
思っていたけれど
I've never really seen him interacting with other people.
あんまり 他人と行動しているのを
見たことがない
Nor have I seen him laughing and talking with people.
笑って誰かと話しているところも
子供のころから
ずっと見ていたけれど—
I've been watching him ever since I was a kid,
but in my memories, he's...
記憶の中の この人は…
That's right.
そうだ　いつも ひとりだ
He's always alone.
Yeah.
そうだ　不思議だ
It's strange.
I played against this guy yesterday.
僕は昨日 この人と戦ったんだ
I played him and lost.
戦って そして負けた
What is this?
何だろう？
この感じは初めてだ
I've never felt this way before.
Even though I lost, I'm not tired at all.
負けたのに 体が全然 疲れていない
I don't feel depressed at all.
気持ちが全然 重くない
I knew I had no chance of winning going in,
勝てるわけがないと思って—
but I had no intention of just giving up.
はなから諦めて当たったわけでは
決して ないつもりだ
ただ 強く分かったことは
経験も研究も—
But I knew deep down that in both experience and studying,
“年の差”という時間の分だけ—
he was years ahead of me, and I wasn't catching up.
圧倒的に
追いつけていないということ
I still had no idea how I could close that gap.
その差は
どうやって詰めたらいいのかも—
まだ分からなかったこと
うまく言えないけれど
負けても すがすがしく—
I can't express it well,
but I've always thought that after a loss,
feeling refreshed or having enjoyed the match
楽しい気持ちでいられるなんて—
is actually a major insult to your opponent.
本当は
相手に とても失礼なことに思える
It's like putting your opponent on a pedestal,
showing reverence, and then personally feeling refreshed.
ただ相手を神棚に祀(まつ)って
勝手に拝んで—
一方的に すっきりしているようで
It's like not thinking of your opponent as a person.
まるで 人を人とも
思っていないような気がして…
（零）
そう思ってきたのに…　なのに…
That's what I've always thought,
何だったんだろう？　昨日の対局は
but how does that account for yesterday's match?
When I'm up against other pros,
no matter how big the skill gap is between us,
ほかの棋士と戦っているときは
どんなに力の差があっても—
I can always trace their line of thinking to some extent.
相手の思考が
ある程度はトレースできるのに…
He's the only one...
彼だけは ただ…
where I drew a blank.
真っ白だった
指している間 ２人で
ずっと真っ白い中にいた
While we were playing,
it felt like the two of us were alone in a pure white space.
And it was very comfortable.
それが とても心地よかった
I wonder what that was yesterday.
（関係者Ｑ）
何だったんでしょうね？　昨日の…
The post-match review with Master Souya and Kiriyama, 5-dan, I mean.
宗谷名人と
桐山五段の感想戦
I've never seen anything like it.
（関係者Ｒ）
あんなの初めて見た
They just kept going without exchanging a single word.
２人とも ひとっ言も
しゃべんないまんま—
進んでいくんだもんな
（関係者Ｓ）対局が終わって
感想戦になったら—
After the match was over and the post-match review began,
いきなり 桐山が—
Kiriyama suddenly lined up all the pieces
with determination without saying a word.
黙って
すごい勢いで—
駒を並べ始めたんだよな
And when they got up to the 63rd move,
（関係者Ｑ）
そして 63手目まで戻って—
he played S-6f, which wasn't in the match record.
本譜にはなかった６六銀を指した
Then Master Souya gave a little nod in response, right?
（関係者Ｑ）宗谷名人
あのとき うなずきましたよね
小さかったけど
He was confirming that Kiriyama's P*7d was the move that lost the match,
（関係者Ｒ）桐山の敗着は
やっぱり あの７四歩で—
and that S-6f, from the post-match review, was a more promising move.
感想戦で指した６六銀が
有望だったということなんだろうな
The most amazing thing is what happened after.
（関係者Ｑ）
…で すごいのは そのあとだ
When the post-match review was over,
桐山が 感想戦が終わったとき—
Kiriyama glanced at his own fingers for a moment.
一瞬 自分の指を
チラッと見たんですよ
He just looked at them.
ただ それだけなのに…
That's what it's like.
（宗谷）そういうもんだよ
What did he mean by that?
（関係者Ｑ）
あれは何だったんでしょうね？
I'm positive "That's what it's like" is what he said.
確かに言ったんですよ 名人が
“そういうもんだよ”って
Kiriyama hadn't even said a word to him.
桐山は ただのひと言も
しゃべってないのに
I was startled by that.
（零）あのとき びっくりしたんだ
I thought maybe I'd blurted out what I was thinking.
考えてたことが
口に出てしまったのかと思った
But it got through to him without words.
言葉にしてないのに通じた
こんな世界があるのかと思った
I thought, "This kind of world exists?"
It was a quiet, bright place
静かで 明るくて 何も—
怖くない所にいた
where there was nothing to be afraid of.
The bullet train arrived at Sendai Station a little past noon and then stopped running.
（零）12時を過ぎて
仙台(せんだい)駅に入ったところで—
新幹線が動かなくなった
Due to the rising water level of the Abukuma River,
service is being suspended.
（アナウンス）阿武隈川(あぶくまがわ)
水位上昇のため運行を見合わせます
なお 運転再開の見通しは
立っておりません
It is not yet determined when service will resume.
繰り返し ご乗車の…
I repeat, will the passengers...
Rush
Zoom
Huh? What?
All the office
workers stand up
the moment they
hear the message
as they're
accustomed to it.
All the office
workers stand up
the moment they
hear the message
as they're
accustomed to it.
（零）えっ？　えっ？　早(はや)っ！
That was fast!
That was
fast!
Service has been suspended due to Typhoon Number Two.
（アナウンス）台風２号の影響で
運行を見合わせております
I repeat, service has been suspended due to Typhoon Number Two.
繰り返します
台風２号の影響で
運行を見合わせております
We apologize for the inconvenience.
お急ぎのところ
大変 申し訳ありません
Service has been suspended due to Typhoon Number Two.
台風２号の影響で
運行を見合わせております
（零）寝てる
He's sleeping.
Souya.
宗谷さん　あの…
Um...
あの…　宗谷さん
Excuse me, Souya.
どうしよう
What should I do?
Excuse me...
（零）あの…
（宗谷）うん？
Sorry, but, um...
すいません
あの…　でも この電車
もう動かないみたいなんで
Apparently, the train has stopped running.
ハァ…
Souya?
（零）宗谷さん？
I guess train service is suspended for today.
今日は もう運転の再開の見込みは
ないみたいだって さっき 放送で…
That's what they announced.
So we'll need to get a refund for our tickets, and then...
なので
チケットの払い戻しと あと…
It looked like I wasn't getting through to him.
（零）何も
届いていないかのような表情に—
My heart started pounding like a jackhammer.
胸がザワザワと騒ぎだした
We'd better get a room for the night.
今晩 泊まる所を押さえないと
全てのピースが合致した
All of the pieces fell into place.
I didn't think I could leave him on his own,
放ってはおけないと思い
手を引いた
so I reached out my hand.
It wasn't that sound seemed to fade out around him.
この人の周りから
音が消えて見えたのではなかった
この人の中に 音がないのだ
It was that
sound didn't exist for him.
Why?
どうして？　いつから？
For how long?
分からない
I don't know.
But nothing reaches his ears anymore.
この人の耳には
もう何も届いてはいないのだ
White Storm (Part 3)
White Storm (Part 4)
（アナウンス）
運転再開の見込みは…
The announcements continued non-stop at the station.
（零）駅にはアナウンスが流れ続け
重たい雨の湿気の中—
Amid the oppressive humidity from the rain, the premises were jammed with people.
構内は
たくさんの人で ごった返していた
今日は もう動かない
It's not going to run until tomorrow.
In that case, we should get a refund for our special express tickets.
…ということは
特急券の払い戻しをすればいいのか
（アナウンス）
台風２号の影響のため…
The ticket line is probably really long.
（零）切符売り場 混んでそうだな
ちょっと出遅れたから
I was a little slow getting off the train.
Um, let's go through the ticket gate.
え〜っと…　それじゃ
いったん 改札を出ましょう
僕が並んで え〜
特急券の精算をしてくるので…
I'll stand in line and take care of the adjustment for the train tickets.
うん？　宗谷さん？
Souya?
Adjustment Window
Thank you.
（零）どうも
I see.
そっか　払い戻しだから
ここでもできるのか　なるほど
We're getting a refund, so we can do it here too.
Makes sense.
Adjustment Window
Now we got our refunds and took care of the tickets for tomorrow.
これで 払い戻しと
乗車券の手続きは済んだから
Um, next... That's right. A place to stay.
え〜っと 次は…　そうだ 泊まる所
泊まる所を確保しないと
We'd better make reservations.
This is a big station, so there must be an information counter.
大きな駅だから
きっと案内板とかが…
Oh, there it is.
あっ あった
Um, which one would be good?
え〜っと…　どれがいいんだ？
It's really coming down, so as close to the station as possible, like a place that's connected to the underground passageways.
とにかく 雨が すごそうだから
なるべく駅から近くて—
地下道とかで つながってる所
（零）そうですか　満室ですか
Really? You're booked?
I understand.
分かりました
ありがとうございます　はい
Thank you.
Okay.
No vacancies at any of the hotels near the station.
駅からすぐのホテルは
もう みんなアウトか
Well, then which hotel should we choose?
でも じゃ あと
ホテルって どれがいいんだ？
If it were just me, any would be fine.
自分だけなら何でもいいんだけど
Seisen Inn?
“盛泉(せいせん)イン”…
あ〜 東京にも よくあるやつだ
Oh, there are a lot of them in Tokyo too.
We can even walk there.
そこなら歩いて行けますね
そんなに遠くない
It's not too far.
Yes, do you have any vacancies?
はい　空いてますか？
はい　シングル ２(ふた)部屋で
Yes. Two single rooms.
はい これから行きます　はい
Yes, we'll head there right now.
Uh-huh.
Seisen Inn
（電話を切る音）
よ〜し 取れました　良かった
All right, we got rooms.
Thank goodness.
Let's go.
さあ 行きましょう
This gray part must be underground,
so let's follow it as far as we can, then take the sidewalk.
（零）きっと
このグレーの所が地下道だから—
Seisen Inn
ギリギリまで下で行って
上に出ましょう
Right. Umbrellas.
そうだ 傘！　傘買わないと
We'd better buy umbrellas.
Empty
There aren't any!
ハッ…　ない！
Sold out in the
blink of an eye
Empty
Ahhh!
Thankfully, that store still had umbrellas.
（零）
良かった　あった　傘ありました
They sell out just like that.
一斉になくなるんですね
危なかった
It was a close one.
さあ 行きましょう
Okay, let's get going.
It didn't feel real.
（零）現実感がなかった
But there was a weird sense of euphoria.
でも 不思議な高揚感があった
It must've been due to the typhoon.
きっと全部 この台風のせいだ
（零）
ウワッ…　タクシー すごい列
Look at that line for taxis!
Whoa, what a downpour!
ウオッ…　雨 すごっ！
Huh?
（零）あれ？　え〜っと…
なんか お店になったぞ
Um...
It seems this path leads to some stores.
こっちから出られるのかな…
Can we get to the sidewalk from here?
Huh?
（零）あれ？
え〜っと これは…　トラック？
Um... This is...
A truck?!
The service entrance?
搬入口か？
こっから出ていいのかな…
Is it okay to exit this way?
おもむろに？
Just like that?!
I need stuff for right now, tonight, and I suppose tomorrow morning.
今の分 夜の分と 朝のか
え〜っと あとは サンドイッチと
おにぎりとカップラーメンと…
Um, also...
A sandwich, a rice ball, cup noodles...
Okay.
よし　うん
That'll do it.
I may be buying too much,
but I don't want to have to go back out in this rain.
買い過ぎかもしれないけど—
この雨じゃ
もう買いに来られないからな
Your total is 1,540 yen.
（店員）合計で1,540円です
That's all?
それだけ？　…ていうか
なにか非常食っぽいラインナップ
It's like a lineup of emergency rations.
Packed Egg
Sandwich
Pork Cutlet Sandwich
Fried Tofu
Pouches
Milk Choux
Cream Bread
Fluffy Melon Bread
（店員）合計で2,980円です
Your total is 2,980 yen.
Huh? Really? That much?
Heap
えっ？　あれ？　そんなに？
Bought
too much
*Apparently
carried away
by the typhoon
situation
*Apparently
carried away
by the typhoon
situation
（ドアチャイム）
（店員）ありがとうございました
Thank you!
I see it.
見えた
I think that's it.
多分 あれだ
Surrounded by a landscape on the verge of permanent stasis
I found myself searching for something
I took up a mask to make my pitifully weak self appear stable
And donned it boldly
The sound of my frozen footsteps as I walked along the river
Was easily overpowered by the roar of a passing train
Yet I kept chanting "I just gotta take another step" to myself
Over and over again
Can you hear me proclaiming that I'm standing right here?
Even in bare feet I can go wherever the hell I want
I don't know where I might find myself at the end
I can't begin to guess, but I can just ink in
A new landscape to suit me as I go
When I start walking,
（零）歩きだすと—
歩きだす
he starts walking.
立ち止まると—
When I stop,
he stops.
立ち止まる
It's like a god
僕のあとを 静かに—
is quietly following me.
神さまがついてくる
White Storm (Part 4)
Next Episode Preview
It's me.
Episode 38
（神宮寺）俺だ 俺
お前 大丈夫か？
Are you okay?
It didn't feel real at all.
（零）現実感が
まるでなかった
Throughout the years,
（神宮寺）
もうずっと—
there are times when he can hear
and times when he can't.
〝聞こえる〞と
〝聞こえない〞を—
行ったり来たりしている
Even though I'm certain the two
of us walked together in the rain.
（零）あの雨の中—
２人で確かに
一緒に歩いたのに…
Illustration: Kamijou Atsushi
（神宮寺）
あそこの露天風呂
最高なんだよな
That open-air hot spring was awesome!
You should've gone in too, Kiriyama.
桐山ちゃんも
入ればよかったのに